Guide to the Michael Tatham collection on the United Taxi Workers Organizing Committee WAG.005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Michael Tatham collection on the United Taxi Workers Organizing Committee
1978-1981
WAG.005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.25 linear feet (1 box)
The United Taxi Workers Organizing Committee (UTWOC) was formed in 1979 in response to a change in many Boston taxicab companies away from an employee-driver basis to one of voluntary leasing. Dissatisfied with the actions of the two existing unions - the Back Bay Taxi Drivers Association and the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 496 - a small group of dissidents concluded that their best hope lay in a new organizing drive. Despite many difficulties, including a high turnover, a broad mix of personal and ethnic backgrounds, and a lack of militant support, the union was able to win recognition from the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) in November 1980. After a brief campaign the union was defeated in a general membership vote on December 5, 1980. The collection contains leaflets relating to organizing and to union elections as well as documents from the UTWOC’s appeal to the NLRB for recognition. An unpublished typescript on the history of the UTWOC by Michael Tatham, an organizer for the union, is also included.
United Taxi Workers Organizing Committee.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The United Taxi Workers Organizing Records were donated to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by Michael Tatham in 1984. The accession number associated with this gift is 1981.001.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The United Taxi Workers Organizing Committee (UTWOC) was formed in 1979 in response to a shift in many Boston taxicab companies, including Checker Taxi and Town Taxi, away from an employee-driver basis to one of voluntary leasing. The drivers contended that this change rendered them powerless to control their hours of work, lease, and gas charges. The two existing unions – the Back Bay Taxi Drivers Association and International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 496 – allegedly did little to protect the drivers.
Boston taxi drivers were difficult to organize because of high turnover and a broad mix of personal and ethnic backgrounds. The UTWOC was founded by a small group of dissidents who concluded, as tension over new employment terms mounted, that their best hope lay in a new organizing drive. Efforts were made throughout the winter of 1979 to 1980 to get drivers at Town Taxi, the city’s second-largest garage, to sign union cards. The high turnover rate of drivers impeded this process, as did the already-established jurisdiction of Teamsters Local 496 and the Back Bay Taxi Drivers Association.
Despite a lack of militant support, UTWOC leaders filed with the National Labor Relations Board for recognition in the summer of 1980. On November 5th, the NLRB ruled in favor of the UTWOC and ordered an election. After a brief campaign in which it was blocked at every turn by management and its agents, the new union was defeated in a general membership vote on December 5, 1980.
Sources:
Tatham, Michael. “UTWOC History.” Unpublished typescript, undated.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains leaflets from the UTWOC and Teamsters, Local 496 relating to organizing and union elections as well as copies of the union’s newsletter. Also present are documents from the union’s appeal to the NLRB for recognition, including proceedings, trial notes, correspondence and correspondence. An unpublished typescript on the history of the UTWOC by Michael Tatham, an organizer for the union, is also included.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
I, General Files, 1978-1981
Back Bay Taxi Drivers Association.; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Stablemen, and Helpers of America. Local 469 (Boston, Mass.).; Tatham, Michael; Boston (Mass.); Correspondence.; Histories.; Leaflets (printed works); Legal documents.; Newsletters.; Taxicab drivers |x Labor unions |z Massachusetts |z Boston.; Taxicabs |z Massachusetts |z Boston.
- Series I: General Files, 1978-1981.
  - Authorization Cards (sample), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Benefit: Leaflets and Tickets, Sep 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Checker Taxi Company: Arbitration, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Checker Taxi Company: Agreement, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - City of Boston Police Department: Rules and Regulations for Hackney Carriages(pamphlet), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Elections, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Finances, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 496: Organizing Leaflets, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Organizing Leaflets, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Proposal for Provisional Constitution, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tatham, Michael: “UTWOC History” (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Town Taxi: Leaflets, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Town Taxi v. UTWOC and Back Bay Taxi Drivers Association: Arbitration, Sep 1980-Nov 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Town Taxi v. UTWOC and Back Bay Taxi Drivers Association: Notes, Aug 1980-Sep 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - United Taxi Workers Organizing Committee Newsletter, Jan 1980-Aug 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)